Kant's emphasis on human dignity has led him
to be called the father of human rights,
and his influence remains strong in modern Germany.
The first article of the Constitution declares that
human dignity shall be inviolable, never to be compromised.
But what happens when respecting someone's dignity prevents
us from acting to save an innocent life?
In 2002, Jakob von Metzler, the 11-year-old son
of a prominent German banking family, was kidnapped.
A few days later, the police arrested Magnus
Gaffgen, after he had collected the ransom money.
But he refused to say where his victim was hidden.
The deputy police chief of Frankfurt.
He told this kidnapper that if he
doesn't tell where the child is hidden,
he would suffer in a
way that he cannot even imagine.
He threatened him with torture.
The threat worked.
Gaffgen admitted that he had already
killed the boy and hidden the body.
He was given a life sentence for murder.
But remarkably, the deputy police chief was also
prosecuted and convicted of violating the kidnapper's rights.
You're trying to save an innocent child, and
here you have the criminal who kidnapped him.
The argument against it is that there
are some inherent qualities in a person
that the person cannot forfeit even
by doing the worst deeds possible.
According to Kantian ethics, you're not allowed to just use a
person, to just abuse him, to hurt him, to torture him,
in order to get something out of him,
even if the purpose of this was good.
Because that's using a person as a
means, rather than respecting him as an end.
Exactly.
Even though he's a criminal, a kidnapper.
Even though it's a criminal, even though we
think he didn't really act terribly, you know, nice,
even though he's a criminal, even though we
even though he's a criminal, even
though he's a criminal, you know, nice,
and he didn't really have
much dignity in his own actions,
why should you treat him,
you know, with respect and dignity?
Exactly.
You are not allowed to treat a
person as a means for another end.
Now, here's what a utilitarian would say.
A utilitarian would say,
you've defended Kant, on his categorical principle,
but you've just shown what's
morally absurd about the Kantian position.
But you've just shown what's
Within the utilitarian way of thinking about
moral issues or moral cases, you cannot distinguish
in the end anymore what kind of action
is good and what kind of action is bad.
It's totally relative.
In some instances it's good to torture,
in other instances it's not good to torture.
What about respect for human dignity?
Well, again, I would say what about
respect for the dignity of the child?
I mean, here's a child who is locked up
somewhere, going to die slowly from hunger and thirst.
There's no way that's a dignified
thing to do to the child.
As a utilitarian, I would say, if I know that
I can save the child and I don't, then I'm
responsible for that child's death.
And that's what, in my view, Kantians
refuse to acknowledge, their responsibility for the
things that they don't do that could save lives.
Now, in the German case...
The kidnapping case, they were confident
that they had identified the perpetrator.
Let's assume that's the case, but the
perpetrator still won't talk, even under torture.
But he would talk if you tortured his 14-year-old daughter.
Would you do it?
I mean, that would be a much harder
case, you know, in an emotional level, I think,
to torture someone who you know has done
something horrible is something that you can psychologically
come at more easily than to torture.
I mean, you can torture somebody who's completely innocent.
So if it's simply the one-on-one case here,
I would say no, because the child that you're
torturing is just as innocent as the child who's dying.
But if there are 10 children who are...
But if you up the numbers, I suppose I'm
going to come under a lot of pressure, and perhaps
I will say, I don't know if I could do
it, but perhaps I would say, if you really knew
that that was going to get
the information to save the 10 children.
Yeah.
Then you would...
Then the right thing to do would
be to torture one to save 10.
Even an innocent girl?
She's innocent, but so are the 10 innocent, of course.
And it's a matter of numbers.
And it's a matter of numbers in the end.
As a war reporter, I have
to say, you know, I can see...
I speak to people who were
victims of this kind of thinking.
You know, if you...
If you...
If you talk to people who were tortured,
badly tortured, exactly with that kind of argument,
it's so evident why you need Kantian thinking
as the guidance, per se, to stop people from
thinking they could use others as a means.
It's for me, that's...
You know, it's...
I see on every single
trip I make to whichever country.
Wherever I speak to people who, you know,
were abused, who were tortured, who were mistreated
with such kind of argument that it's...
It's full purpose.
There's a good end to this.
There's a reason why we could torture people.
It's devastating to see that.
So I'm...
You know, I'm deep...
I'm deeply convinced that Kantian thinking is...
Is the best guidance we have to protect human rights.
And I think that's...
I think that's...
I think that's the key to our rights.
The von Metzler case prompted much
debate over Germany's constitutional commitment to
human dignity.